[Music]
sh
to for
[Music]
fore fore
uh you can be a good scholar he's
talking about Christopher I introduced
you he said you can be a good scholar
even if you don't have to wear robs so
it's
okay H we didn't get too far did
[Laughter]
we uh we didn't exactly finish that last
hassle we had like you may think it's
finished but it's not finished uh we're
on page 10 last line and we still got a
little bit left to do about that last
argument we had
[Music]
so don't forget we have two ways of
viewing an object uh that were just
mentioned and they were talking about
whether one state of mind could hold
both of them at the same time one was uh
to see things in a in a way which exists
by definition according to the mind only
school's explanation of what it is to
Exist by definition and could you at the
same time uh hold the same object to uh
was it not exist by uh to Exist by
definition in the way that the maika
school explains it and we decided that
you could right or you couldn't that you
could now now he's going to talk a
little bit about those two modes of
viewing an object of modes of viewing
nominal objects
right you sure it's
okay yeah you guys got the the former
and the latter we're talking about
former being the way the mind only
School thinks that something would Exist
by definition and latter being the way
that the uh majima School thinks exist
something would Exist by definition
right right okay so there two modes of
looking at
something fore
[Music]
so uh don't forget the two distinctions
that we're making and don't forget the
object with we're talking about which is
his Rosary which represents all things
which are nominal don't forget that all
nominal things means unchanging objects
in the universe after you take out
emptiness right so in the mind only
School uh nominal stuff refers to all
the objects in the world which are
unchanging after you take out emptiness
itself and don't forget that when they
are talking about an object they say
that those things cannot exist by
definition as existing by definition is
explained in in their own School uh
because they don't have existence from
their old side right uh so true identity
from their own side and and then but
they do have a uh they do have some
definitive existence or they do exist by
definition as explained by the majima
school because maika school says the the
measure of something existing by
definition is that when you look for the
thing that's given the name independent
of the name you do find an object okay
that which they say doesn't even exist
but don't forget that in this school
they're talking about uh these are great
Scholars of the of the Mind only school
and they're saying don't forget the
object we're talking about is nominal
objects and in our school they do not
exist uh uh by definition meaning uh
that they don't exist uh what you say
from their own side they exist in
imagination only and they do exist uh by
definition as existing by definition is
described by the manika because manika
says existing by definition means that
when you look for the thing independent
of your projection or independent of the
name you do find something so so don't
forget that those are the distin being
being made here and one more Point uh
don't forget that the mind only School
even though intellectually they
understand that this thing can't Exist
by definition if you pressed them and
you said do you see it as existing by
definition they'd say yeah I do have a
innate uh tendency from my past life to
hold things are self-existent which in
their school means I do have an innate
tendency in my mind to see things as
existing by definition in the way that
existing by definition is described in
the mind only
so even though we don't intellectually
believe that we would say yeah we we are
holding things that way uh anyway even
the imaginary things KX things
okay uh so we finish one big section and
we can just leave it behind now
okay so we finished remember in the
original Sutra in which the Buddha
explains the intent of his own sutras
which is the main text that the mind
only School uses to explain these
Concepts in there it describes three
different kinds of not having their own
nature right and so the first one was
not not having any nature of its own by
definition or in its own definitive
defin and that was referring to kak or
or what do you call you can say
imaginary things or or you know
imaginary stuff like that and that that
we finished that whole section has been
completed now now we're going on to the
second phrase in the original Sut that
talked about things that have no nature
of having
any do you remember beginning having any
beginning they don't have any nature of
having beginning so we finished the ones
that said they have no nature of having
any characteristics of their own which
means is referring to objects which are
uh what we call the nominal stuff right
and now we're on to the second
category fore
so don't forget uh that we we have
finished explaining the first kind of
nature that things don't have and now
he's going on to explain the second kind
of nature that things don't have and if
you recall uh Jess CA said you know I
have opened your eyes to the meaning of
the Sutra and don't forget to use these
two uh these two different explanations
one a positive side one a negative side
one saying it has a certain quality one
saying denying a certain quality don't
forget to use those two when we get to
the bottom twoo remember he said later
on we're going to cover the other two
lacks of a self nature and when we get
to those don't forget to that you have
to use the same reasoning which is a a
short uh explanation from the Sutra and
then a positive explanation and a
negative explanation so now you you do
that logical statement the same way we
did before uh so what is the subject
going to be uh let's consider all things
which are dependent right
uh they don't have any nature of
starting from their own you know of
their own right because and then you're
going to prove it with a positive reason
and negative reason in the same way that
you did
before for
what you want it you go let me see if I
can get this straight uh when they talk
about the positive reasoning and the
negative reasoning for proving that
starting of things things don't have any
nature of starting of their own accord
right uh what that means uh that the
there are two ways in scripture of
explaining the positive and the negative
reasonings okay so two different ways of
explaining what it means with regard to
things which are dependent which means
all things which are caused right the
most most of the things around us so
from a positive point of view when
you're trying to prove that they have no
nature of their own all you have to say
is because they come from their causes
and conditions and that's enough of a
proof to say that they don't have that
starting or the beginning of things the
growing of things doesn't have any
nature of its own uh in a negative way
you could say they don't go grow from a
self in the way that a self is explained
by the suia school of non- Buddhists
okay there's a siia school numerous uh
they're called soall because they they
divide things into many categories like
so many existing categories they believe
that there is a self which is which
exists before something grows which is
not separate from that thing uh and then
it just reveals itself you know so that
in in a way the thing has always been
there so to prove that things don't have
a nature of growing by themselves you
can do it in a positive way by saying
look it doesn't have a nature of growing
on its own because it comes from its
causes and conditions and from a
negative way you can say it doesn't have
a nature of growing on its own because
that idea of that non- Buddhist school
that things grow from themselves in a
sense is false okay that's one way of
explaining the the positive and the
negative proof the other way of explain
the positive negative proof is like
consider all uh things which are which
uh what should I say consider all things
which are dependent meaning dependent on
other causes uh they don't grow of their
own accord they don't have any nature of
growing by themselves because they are
not something which doesn't depend on
its causes okay so then you're saying
just the same thing in a negative way
that's another way of explaining the
negative proof in that case the
corresponding positive proof is the same
it doesn't have a nature of growing on
its on its own because it comes from
causes and conditions or to State it
negatively it doesn't have a uh it
doesn't have a nature of growing on its
own because it is not such that it
doesn't grow from its causes and
conditions and that's the negative one
so there's two ways of explaining with
regard to dependent things uh why uh
it's doesn't have a nature of growing on
its
own fore
uh just about the same pattern of
reasoning used to prove that the second
attribute of the Mind only School uh
doesn't have any nature of its own the
second group of things doesn't have any
nature of its own the same pattern that
we had with the first one that Jetson CA
said remember this pattern because it's
going to be repeated and the scripture
said the original Sutra said uh it first
the original Sutra said something kind
of obscure it said nothing has a nature
of growing uh and then the Buddha said
what do I mean when I say it doesn't
have a nature of growing I mean that it
that things which are dependent don't
have a nature of growing that was the
first part of the answer right there was
a rhetorical question and then the
Buddha answered himself right what did I
mean when I said things don't have a m a
nature of growing I was talking about uh
things which are dependent that category
U mind only School category of things
which are dependent they don't have a
nature of growing what do I here comes
the second rhetorical question what do I
mean when I say that I mean they don't
have uh from a positive Viewpoint uh
they do have a nature of growing from
their causes and conditions and from a
negative Viewpoint they were never
anything other than having a nature of
growing from their conditions and causes
and conditions and that's the the full
presentation following the same pattern
that was used in the case of the first
category of things out of the three
categories right
uh as you may remember we are in the
expanded explanation detailed
explanation of what has already been
presented earlier in what was called a
briefer explanation so in the line
beginning from uh uh really it's about
[Music]
the yeah we're on uh page 11 line four
and that's where you get uh Jon cop is
starting to give his uh his own
explanation of the suus explanation of
what the Buddha meant when he said that
things don't have a nature of growing
okay
M uh Jessa as usual wants to stop here
and make a clarification so that people
start don't start getting the wrong idea
so don't forget that the all the Buddha
said was that things don't have a nature
of growing okay and then uh then he
explained himself and said things don't
when I say things don't have a nature of
growing what I mean is that things which
are dependent on other things to to grow
don't have a nature of growing and
jetona says therefore Lord Buddha is not
saying that those things which are
dependent on other things meaning uh
cause things right that they don't have
any nature of growing at all that's not
what he's saying it's not saying that
they don't grow or something like that
or denying that things which have causes
and conditions grow or something like
that he's saying dependent things do
grow but dependent things don't grow by
themselves and he has to add just like
says You must add those words by
themselves because by themselves those
words block or or they prevent people
from thinking that uh things which are
dependent don't come from their causes
and conditions so once you say once you
say to somebody look when I said things
don't have a nature of growing uh Lord
Buddha meant they don't have a nature of
thing a nature of growing on their own
and on their own implies that they don't
have a nature of growing without their
own causes and conditions and that's
what the Lord Buddha means when he says
things don't have a nature of growing
but don't think the Lord Buddha thinks
that nothing grows or something like
that fore
and then J CA comes up and says I'm not
just making this explanation up you know
I'm not just like uh giving you some
explanation about what the Buddha said
that I've just made up you know when he
says uh when the Buddha says things
don't have a nature of growing the
Buddha means they don't have a nature of
growing on their own uh and that means
they don't have a nature of growing
without their causes and conditions uh
jokaa wants to impress on people this is
not just my idea this is not just my
interpretation about the Buddhist saying
I've got scriptural Authority uh to show
you for that and we can quote again
master who's the big founder of the Mind
only School remember we're trying to
prove that it's true for the mind only
school so he says I can quote Master s
because the follow it's the following
like line of reasoning uh when the
Buddha said that things don't have a
nature of growing what he meant was
things don't have a nature of growing on
their own and what growing on your own
means is growing without causes and
conditions or growing independently and
J Kaa says I can show you that that uh
aanga has said the same thing that that
what the Buddha meant when he said
things don't have a nature of growing is
that they don't have a nature of growing
on their own without their causes and
and condition and then he's going to go
ahead and give you uh the meaning of
Aang's quotation now this is a quotation
from the same work by Master sang to
back up that that's what he that's how
he understands what the Buddha meant
when the Buddha said things don't have a
nature of going on their own and
remember that there were two ways to
describe in a negative sense why things
uh why things that that depend uh don't
have a nature of growing on their own uh
one of them was kind of easy like uh
things don't have a nature of growing on
their own because there's nothing which
doesn't grow from its causes and
conditions that was one negative way of
saying it then the other negative way of
saying was that things don't have these
things these dependent things don't have
a nature of growing on their own because
they don't have a nature of growing from
a cause which is one with them which is
the belief of a certain non- Buddhist
School the samka so he says if you think
about it Master sa is not so much
stressing that second interpretation of
the negative reasoning he's more going
after the first interpretation which
means things don't grow on their own
means things don't grow independently
means things don't grow without their
causes and conditions but he's not so
much going out to the reasoning that
things don't grow on their own because
things don't grow by themselves meaning
that things don't grow from a cause
which is one with them and which existed
earlier than them because that's a
certain idea that's how a certain Hindu
School thinks that things appear in the
world it's like they existed already and
then somehow they are revealed or
something like that he says that's he
doesn't go so much after that one as
after the first one okay
uh so you might wonder where this
explanation came of the two negative
reasonings like the one that Master s
seems to be stressing is that uh things
don't have a nature of growing because
things don't have a nature of growing on
their own because things don't have a
nature of growing
in any way except from causes and
conditions right that's one way to State
the negative one and the other one is
like well the S girl used to say that
things Grew From themselves in a sense
and they were there before they started
and the and then they were just revealed
or something like that and he says you
don't see that so much in this text but
in our C textbooks that's what they
stress you know they stress this idea
which Jessa discusses in other great
books that what it means not to grow by
yourself is is actually just C is and
the Buddha are trying to refute this
idea that was common in India that the
thing is actually growing from itself in
a sense that it existed before and then
its growth is some kind of a revelation
of its existence that was actually there
before so uh in our C textbooks uh they
are stressing that second Point more
than you might be aware of if you just
read this text by J
fore
uh the reason he went into that little
uh aside about what our C textbooks say
about this point is that he realizes
that once we get back to America I'll
probably end up teaching this to you
guys at some point and then me having
such uh loyalty to sarame I'll probably
dig out the sarame textbook and I'll
probably be stressing the other one
because if Michael had to choose between
the two interpretations he'd probably go
for the one that's in the textbook more
because he likes the textbook so much
and then you guys would start thinking
maybe he's making this up but then
you'll think oh no we heard Gish talk
about that second one back back in India
so I guess it's
okay so he's just trying to anticipate a
possible problem
there uh then uh
what do I know says G you know I mean
I'm not just a dumb old guy but uh you
know the great masters of history have
explained this in two different ways and
you should know that because if you just
read this text by itself you wouldn't be
aware that some great Masters have
explained it the other way as well so
there's a definitely a great benefit to
explaining it both ways and who am I I
don't know anything about either way but
but it's good if you understand that
there are two ways of explaining this
point
uh there are two very benefit icial
realizations you can have from the two
presentations because the second
presentation uh which says things are
not such that they don't grow from their
causes and conditions you know makes you
aware that a thing cannot grow it's
denying it's giving you like a mental
picture of something growing without any
causes or conditions at all and then
it's denying that that thing but the
benefit of the other one is that it's
it's stressing that things don't grow
from things which seem to be causes but
which are not causes so that one's not
talking about about you don't get a
mental picture of something without any
causes at all you get a mental picture
of something which has a supposed cause
but that thing has Mis been
misidentified as a cause it's not really
a cause for that thing so in the first
case you're getting sort of this mental
picture of of denying that things could
grow without causes and then in the
second case you're getting this sort of
nice mental picture of denying that
things could grow from things which
people think are causes but which are
not causes for them and those both have
their own separate benefits to think
about both of
them fore
[Music]
uh when the Buddha said things don't
have a nature of growing right he's
talking about things which are dependent
right the category or the group that the
mind only School talks about which are
really all cause things things which are
dependent and if you think about it uh
there are two ways uh of explaining why
things which are dependent don't have a
nature of growing and you can explain it
either according to the mind only system
or you can also explain it according to
the consequent you consequence system or
the pro EOS system among the uh Middle
Way schools the higher of the two middle
way schools so really when you get to
this point when you're trying to explain
what the Buddha meant when he said
things don't have a nature of growing
you can either explain it according to
the mind only school or you can explain
it according to the consequence School
group among the middleway school which
is the highest explanation of it
[Music]
even if you just restrict yourself to
this Sutra which as you remember is
called the Sutra in which the Buddha
explains what he really meant when he
taught the sutras right uh and and if
you just restrict your self to that
there is a explanation that's going
along the mind only School way and
there's a separate exp explanation
that's going along the consequence
groups of the middle way school's
explanation right and I can repeat for
you the first one's idea the mind only
school's idea is that what it means when
you say that things don't have a nature
of growing is that you are saying that
things don't have a nature of growing
without any causes and conditions but
when you get to the Mika praga
explanation of what the Buddha meant
when he said don't have a nature of
growing he meant things don't have a
nature of growing in such a way that
they exist that exists by definition in
the way that the MIM schools explains
what existing by definition means which
you guys surely
remember uh we gotta lock that mik door
again you can't go over there okay stick
to the Min only scho
uh so we're back in the middleway school
I'm sorry M only School the Buddha has
said that things don't have a nature of
growing uh does don't have a nature of
growing and then you know now that he's
talking about dependent things or cause
things and uh the Buddha is denying that
they have any kind of a nature of
growing and how would you guys choose to
describe what the Buddha meant according
to the mind only school when he said
things don't have a nature of growing
what did he mean what did he have in
mind what was he trying to do what was
he trying to
say can't go that way my my J room is
shut door is shut got to go M only but
you're in the M only suit now so what
did what what did he say when he said
that things don't have a nature of
growing oh that's the right way to go
yeah that's how you have to go
uh if you're going to sit in a in a mind
only suit and then try to move go into
the might mikor it wouldn't be
appropriate and you've gone the right
way so since you've got a m only suit on
uh you've gone into the M only way of
explaining it and you did it right thank
you
okay uh so now I'm quite convinced that
all of you are of a single mind
stream because uh only one of you chose
to speak so I assume there's only one
mind running all these bodies in here
and uh I'm sure uh if you had all had
your own mind streams you probably would
have all answered me at the same time
uh when you get into the army you know
uh there's everybody lined up in
regimental uh columns you know and then
the marching Master says okay everybody
raise their hand and there just and all
the hands come up at the same time so I
guess it's almost like uh one mind
running all these bodies so I suppose we
just have one uh mental stream here
that's running all these bodies just
like in the Army you
know just kidding
so we'll take that second discussion
which is of the cause things right
dependent things and we'll leave it
aside for now and we'll go on to the
next one that seems sounds like a m to
me
[Music]
M uh so we finished among the three
groups that are positive by the minority
school we have finished what the Buddha
meant when he said things don't have any
characteristic right they don't have any
nature of having any characteristics
which refer to uh
was it young things right was
it things sorry the the uh nominal stuff
and then we finished the second group
where we talked about uh that the things
that grow don't have any nature of their
own things don't have any nature of
growing on their own which is finishing
off the second group which is called
Shen Wang uh dependent on others and
let's close those two doors we've uh
locked this up we've locked this up now
we're on to the third group uh which is
the last group we got to go into the
mind only school's interpretation of
what it means in the third group when
the Buddha said uh things don't have any
nature of being ultimate and he says
again we have two options on how to
explain uh what the Buddha meant when he
said things don't have a nature of being
ultimate uh I'm only talking about two
different ways of explaining the lack of
a nature of being ultimate and don't
take this two explanations and go carry
them to the first two okay this is just
with reference to the third group okay
the way in which there are two ways of
explaining what the Buddha meant when he
said that things don't have a nature of
being ultimate the first one is the way
in which uh things which depend on
others are not ultimate and the second
is explaining how things which are what
we call Total existence or emptiness are
not ultimate so actually we're
describing the lack of
ultimacy uh with the second group and
the lack of ultimacy with the third
group is the meaning of lack of ultimate
when you're talking about the third
group okay
[Music]
uh so when we say that there's no
ultimate nature of being ultimate with
regard to things which are dependent
meaning cause things and then there's no
nature of being ultimate with regard to
things which are total existence meaning
emptiness right so we are dividing into
two kinds of ultimate aren't we and when
you say they don't have this nature of
being ultimate in that way these these
things don't have the nature of being
ultimate in that way caus things and
these things meaning emptiness doesn't
have a nature of being ultimate in that
way what we're really positing is two
kinds of ultimateness which don't even
exist
okay uh we're page 11 third line from
the bottom for those of you are
following the Tibetan
[Music]
uh then uh the text itself here three
lines from the bottom of page 11 says in
the Third Kind of a lack of nature which
as you know now refers to the lack of
nature of being ultimate uh there are
two ways of positing this lack of Nature
and we're going to talk first about now
the next line says let's discuss how to
determine and what it means to have a
lack of nature for things which are
dependent so now he's already off into
the first meaning of the of the two ways
in which things are not ultimate
[Music]
uh so uh the first of the two ways of
explaining how things don't have a
nature of being ultimate is going to be
covered uh which is by the way the way
in which changing things or things which
depend on the causes uh don't have a
nature of being ultimate is going to be
expressed by a quotation from the Sutra
in which Buddha explained the meaning of
his other suas right and that begins at
the last line on page 11 and continues
up to the seventh line on page 12 so
that will be the actual Sutra uh
presentation of what Lord Buddha meant
when he said things don't have an
ultimate nature changing things don't
have an ultimate nature don't have a
nature of being ultimate and then as you
can assume uh J CER will go ahead and
tear apart the Su quotation for you and
explain it
further itself and in each case the
explanation of what ultimate means is a
little tricky and a little bit different
this one refers to what we call uh
ultimate truth when you describe
ultimate truth as that object which is
perceived by the direct perception of
someone who's perceiving emptiness
directly right when we describe ultimate
truth as that object which is perceived
by an EMP a person who's perceiving
emptiness directly the reason we call
that object ultimate truth or ultimate
reality is that it's being perceived by
the ultimate state of mind so the word
ultimate as applied to Ultimate Reality
actually refers to the state of mind
which perceived emptiness directly as
being the ultimate state of mind so when
you describe its object as Ultimate
Reality the adjective ultimate actually
refers to the state of mind which is
perceiving it and not to the object and
this is this uh Ultimate Reality in the
mind only school is being denied of
things which have causes okay Ultimate
Reality in that sense is being denied of
things which have causes and I hope he
gets into more I'm sure he will uh the
other kind of ultimate refers to uh the
ultimate gaka and you guys know what
gaka means so the ultimate thing which
we deny exists and once we deny it we
reach emptiness so the second kind of
ultimate refers to the ultimate object
that we deny has any existence in order
to come to emptiness and that is a kind
of ultimate which is denied by the mind
only school with regard to emptiness
itself right so you have this ultimate
uh the second ultimate which is the
ultimate object to be denied being being
refuted with regard to emptiness or what
we call Total existence and then the
other kind of ultimate which means uh
the Ultimate Reality and the ultimate
dare coming from the state of mind which
precedes emptiness directly being denied
of things which have causes things which
are dependent now how that's going to
happen I have to see
okay nothing
nothing so the the first meaning if you
take it this way over here right when he
said that uh changing things or things
that depend on and their causes and
results don't have any ultimate nature
right don't have any nature of being
ultimate what it means is that uh that
ultimate nature which is perceived what
Gish calls the path of total Purity path
of total Purity which is uh means the
direct perception of emptiness T right
so the path of total Purity in which one
sees emptiness directly that object
which one sees which is Ultimate Reality
right is is not a thing that depends on
its causes and results so in that sense
it's right it's an uncaused thing right
so that being Ultimate Reality is
uncaused so you can't describe things
which are dependent or which come from
their causes as as being things which
are Ultimate Reality because Ultimate
Reality is an unchanging thing or things
like that so ultimate in that sense is
being refused or refuted of things which
have their own causes not meaning that
they don't have Ultimate Reality but
meaning that they are not ultimate
reality and in that case that's what the
Buddha meant in the first half of this
presentation when he said things that
have depend on their causes and
conditions don't have a nature of being
ultimate meaning they are not Ultimate
Reality okay
so you could summarize uh this
reputation of their having a nature of
being ultimate very simply by saying
things which have things which are
dependent things which are dependent on
their causes and conditions are not that
Ultimate Reality which is the object of
what we call the path of total Purity
which is a c for the direct direct
perception of emptiness okay so that's
how you could describe that one they
things which depend are dependent in the
sense that coming from their causes and
conditions are not the object upon which
the direct perception of emptiness which
is here called the path of total Purity
uh are not the object which it perceives
okay so in that sense we're denying uh a
nature of being ultimate of of things
which change
now this very last thing that we said
about it not being the object of you
know put a big star next to that in your
notes because we're going to come back
to this in a real big argument okay
there's going to be a real uh heavy
argue you better put a mark there
because we're coming back to that point
because there's a big argument about
it
[Music]
fore uh now now having just said what we
just said it's going to incite a big
fight which is not the fight he was
talking about before okay now another
fight somebody's immediately going to
jump up and say well if that's what it
means not to have a nature which is
Ultimate then why are you restricting it
to dependent things isn't it true of
those nominal things they're don't have
a nature of being ultimate right the
other group uh they're not Ultimate
Reality you could say of them also that
they are they don't have a nature of
being ultimate because they are not the
object which the path of total Purity
which is direct perception of emptiness
perceives so why are you just saying it
about things that have causes and you're
not saying it about that other category
of things that were just
nominal so what do you guys think is it
justice uh if we say would it be just
you know would it be fair to say well uh
since things which are dependent or
things which have their own causes are
don't have a nature of being ultimate in
so far as they are not the object which
the ultimate State of Mind perceives
right the direct perception emptiness do
you think it'd be Justice or fair to say
well then we got to go ahead and say
about that other group of things which
are nominal right which are just
constructs of our imagination right a
constructs of our mind to be fair we'd
have to go over to them and say well
they don't have a nature being ultimate
either do what you guys think would it
be fair or
not if you think about it it's the same
thing isn't
it but if you view it from this single
aspect without any other qualifications
right from this single aspect of it not
being that object which the ultimate
State of Mind is is perceiving from and
no nothing else said no other
qualifications from that single point of
view they are absolutely the same it
it's Total Justice and fair to go to
that other group and say well then you
got to say it doesn't have a nature of
being ultimate because to be fair it's
also not the object of the ultimate
State of Mind meaning the direct
possession
emptiness you know
[Music]
and jenta himself is forced into the
same position of saying to that guy who
just made this objection he says you
know uh just from that one point of view
I have to admit that if there was any
justice in the world
that we'd have to say that that other
group is also lacks any nature of having
the ultimate being ultimate and yeah
yeah you're right you're right so let's
add a little bit of a qualification
here uh five lines from the bottom page
12 uh if we were he's on the 12th line
it's 12th page five lines from the
bottom and and the Tibetan says yeah if
you only are making this Distinction on
the basis of it not being the object of
the path of total Purity meaning direct
perception emptiness I admit you'd have
to say that it applies to those
constructs as well
but the reason we said this that that we
described things which have causes as
not having a nature of being ultimate
and the reason we didn't describe the
com constructs as not having a nature of
being ultimate the reason we did that
was because of certain wrong ideas in
the students Minds we have to address
the tendency of students to have a wrong
idea of about changing things that most
students wouldn't have about a mental
construct and that's why the Buddhist
only said it about things which are
changing about things which are
dependent only about those things did
they say they don't have a nature of
being ultimate because that's the one
where most students have a problem
listen uh the point here is that normal
students normal people tend to get a
misconception about whether or not
things that come from their causes
dependent things right uh have a nature
of being ultimate but they don't tend to
get the same misconception about mental
constructs so since the normal tendency
of people is to have a misconception
about one and not to have a
misconception about the other we are
talking more about the fact that things
that are dependent on their causes and
conditions don't have a nature being
ultimate that's why we focus on that one
and we don't focus on the other one
because people tend to have a
misconception about the former and not
about the
latter
[Music]
foree
fore uh since you guys have had some
teachings in the maim mik presentation
and not so much in the mind only
presentation let's crack that door open
a little bit and let you peep in on the
other side okay so the distinction here
why people have a problem with ultimate
nature with regard to things which are
caused is the following when you are
perceiving the emptiness of for example
a chair or let's talk about a water
pitcher and when you are perceiving it
directly uh The Emptiness of that it's
not as if you're having any other
thoughts about it you're not analyzing
it you're not thinking about it that's
not the the way it is but before that
happens for a long time you have to
somebody has to take you take you give
you a water picture saying okay now
check this out look at how this is think
about it this is why it's empty this is
why it's empty you know this is what
it's nature is and then after a lot of
discussion and teaching and instruction
and thinking about it then you get a
very very clear idea a very accurate
idea of what it means for this thing not
to have its own nature so that's that's
how you do it you know especially in the
in the majima school it's all based on
thinking about the object first the
thing that has emptiness and then
discussing the emptiness which the thing
has that's what he meant when he put his
glasses on his on the palm of his hand
he said then you get into discussing the
emptiness which it things has and from
that point of view you you go about
establishing The Emptiness of a of a v
or a
picture
for uh the reason that students might
get into having a confusion or a
suspicion or a
misconception that things which come
from their causes and conditions might
be having a nature which is Ultimate
rather than the things which are con uh
constructs right the reason you more
likely to get into hot water with the
first one is from being aware or
understanding that the process of un of
perceiving a thing's emptiness first
depends on examining the thing which is
empty and then secondly exam ing The
Emptiness of the thing then it might pop
up in a student's mind that when I'm
perceiving emptiness directly well first
I focus on the vase and then I focus on
its emptiness so then they start the the
vase and The Emptiness start to to merge
a little bit and then they might get
this uh doubt or they might get this
misconception that somehow the vase
itself is is Ultimate Reality because
because they've heard that when you're
trying to establish intellectually The
Emptiness of a vase first you have to
examine the vase think about it uh
examine it and then establish its
emptiness so they might think students
might think that during the direct
perception of emptiness that you go
through a similar process focusing on
the vase and then focus on emptiness and
the vase somehow being the pivot around
which you see emptiness and then you
might start having this misconception
that somehow the vase is Ultimate
Reality somehow so that's why Buddha
took special care to deny the things
which have causes and conditions are
have a nature of being ultimate okay
uh we went in that crack in the door to
the manum we brought it out that example
we're going to employ that example here
in our explanation of the Mind only
please be careful to shut the door okay
uh go back shut that door don't let it
leak out anymore okay and now take that
example and apply it to the mind only
school which is very very similar so the
Min only school is saying look uh if we
talk about things which are dependent
meaning things which grow from other
things and they also understand that
during the intellectual stages of trying
to intellectually understand emptiness
you first focus on the vase and then you
focus on its various aspects of being
empty but the vase being the pivotal
object which you are examining when you
talk about emptiness they might here
especially in the mind only school
people might start to focus on the vases
being something caused being the the
center of your focus during the direct
perception of emptiness which would
imply automatically that the Visas
itself was some kind of Ultimate Reality
because everybody knows you only see
Ultimate Reality during your direct
perception emptiness so they they they
start mistaking the the basis of
Ultimate Reality for the Ultimate
Reality and because of the tendency of
people to have that misperception Lord
Buddha takes special care to deny a
nature of being ultimate about things
which have causes and uh conditions and
doesn't apply it to things which are
Concepts even though it does apply to
con things which are
Concepts fore
uh now it seems to me that the a
question should pop up in your mind and
that's you know when I isn't the same
thing true when I'm trying to establish
the emptiness of my con constructs I
mean when I'm trying to establish the
emptiness of my constructs don't I have
to examine those constructs first focus
on those constructs think about those
constructs look at those constructs in
all different ways and then slowly come
to an understanding of their emptiness
you know you should be asking me you
know well it's about the same process
isn't it you have to look at the
constructs you have to focus on them
then you establish their emptiness and
wouldn't it occur to you just as easily
the misconception that constructs are
the are the central focus of the direct
perception of emptiness and therefore
have some nature of being ultimate
CH no they change which change mind
CH that you're going to get in trouble
[Laughter]
now that could
he says uh you're you're almost
anticipating something that comes later
in the text but we'll leave it for now
but it but it's a pretty good idea and
it's actually going to come in the text
later something very
similar if you just look at it on the
face of things uh there's just about no
distinction between the two even with
constructs the process is exactly the
same you have to focus on the concept
you have to think about it
intellectually you have to establish its
emptiness and then you'd probably get in
just as easily into the same
misconception that during the D direct
perception of emptiness you're somehow
perceiving the construct itself and
somehow that's becoming Ultimate Reality
so if you just look at it on the face of
things there's not much difference in
probably we should say that they don't
have a nature of being ultimate
but you
[Laughter]
for foree
uh if you think about it which ones of
the three groups exist according to the
mind only School let's shut that maim
Mika door uh if you stick to the mind
only school if you think about it of the
three groups uh two of them according to
the mind only School exist really or in
truth you know and then the third one
which is those mental constructs
according to the mind only school they
don't describe them as existing in truth
so although it's true that you could
examine mental constructs come to an
understanding of their emptiness because
in the mind only school they are not
considered to exist in the with the same
reality that the other two are said to
exist especially the one being the
ultimate object of the ultimate State of
Mind Right which is the emptiness itself
has some kind of true existence and
things which work and things which
function and things which you can touch
obviously have some true existence but
in this school things mental constructs
don't have that kind of true existence
so a student would be less likely to
have the misconception that those things
those things could have some kind of
ultimate nature or nature of being
ultimate and that's why uh the tendency
with cause things or dependent things is
much stronger to think that they could
have some timate nature than it because
they are said to be truly existing than
it would be with mental constructs which
are in this school said to not have any
true existence or not to exist in in
reality okay
[Music]
so again to repeat uh of course mental
constructs and things which come from
causes are can both be the basis uh for
an emptiness that we perceive when we
perceive emptiness directly and you
could have the same misconception with
both of them but because one of them uh
has what we call a true existence and
this school is said to exist truly and
the other one doesn't have such such a
true existence in this school than the
the Buddha Lord Buddha said was took
more care to isolate things which come
from their causes or which are dependent
and say look they don't have a nature of
being ultimate don't mistake them for
the ultimate for the emptiness which
they have when you're talking about
seeing emptiness directly just because
when you understand emptiness
intellectually you first have to take
them as the basis
[Music]
please refer back to where I told you
you better make a
mark okay and the The Logical statement
there was sh let's talk about things
which come from their caus which
dependent on their causes and conditions
uh they don't have any nature of being
ultimate because they are not the object
which the ultimate state of mind uh
directly perceives right and he says now
I want you to go back there and put a
little comma at the end of the reason
and say and people are more likely to
have a misconception about these you see
what I mean and then your reason is
airtight okay but if you don't have that
you're going to have a problem because
uh construct
the same thing can be said about
constructs but Lord Buddha didn't say
about constructs that they don't have a
nature of being ultimate now you got an
airtight one if you put comma and people
are more likely to have misconception
about them then you're
[Music]
covered uh don't think this is something
that I get you to is just making up and
I think it's a cute explanation or
something like that it's right here in
jet ca's writings but you got to be
sensitive to catch that's what he's
saying and if you're sensitive to it and
you read it carefully you'll catch that
that's the point of what he's saying so
I'm just taking out the real meaning of
what Jessa is actually saying and you
can find it in here if you look
carefully don't think it's something I'm
making up
okay fore
for shut up nothing uh what I said is
coming directly out of this wording that
starts on page 12 uh fourth line for the
bottom and he says I could go through
and explain to L guni it's it's with
reference to trying to to refute
misconceptions that people have that uh
that uh and and the fact that even
though it's to state that with that Shen
Wang itself that things which come from
their causes and conditions themselves
are not the object of the path of purity
meaning the direct perception of
emptiness and and and and why don't we
deny that with regard to con constructs
you know why do we deny it with regard
to cause things and we don't deny it
with regard to constructs uh we don't
okay why is that so a second line from
the bottom on page 12 well the point is
that uh people understand that to
perceive emptiness uh of things which
come from their causes first you have to
focus on those things and then come to
an understanding intellectually of their
emptiness and then come to perceive
their emptiness directly and then people
might have the uh the understanding that
you must examine the object before you
see its emptiness people might think
that during the direct perception of
emptiness you perceive not only the
emptiness but that object too which
would make it Ultimate Reality also can
make it have it somewhere else and this
kind of misconception is much more
common people are much more likely to
get that now we're on to the fourth line
page 13 but with regard to things which
are con instructs uh people are are not
likely to have that particular
misconception and that's Jetson capa's
uh presentation of that whole thing that
I just described
here not
again uh and then to to further clarify
what he's talking about about the ease
with which a certain misconception might
arise in certain people's minds and not
in other people's minds then J Kaa goes
ahead and gives you an illustration to
to show his
[Music]
point for
uh now Jessa gives an illustration to
prove what he was saying and don't
forget what we're trying to prove is
that be very careful here when you
perceive emptiness directly you are
perceiving the emptiness of a certain
object but that even though you're you
you have focused on that object and are
now perceiving its emptiness it's not
the point that you are perceiving that
object while you perceive its emptiness
okay it's it's what you're focusing on
in order to see emptiness but it is not
the emptiness which you are perceiving
okay so there's a similar distinction in
understanding that sounds have a subtle
impermanence that sound itself has some
kind of subtle impermanence it's very
famous in Buddhist logic text okay so he
says consider the state of mind which
believes that sound does not have a
subtle impermanence okay if is that
State of Mind permanently and pushed
aside forced out of your head when you
perceive sound
itself no okay so when you perceive that
uh when you are perceive sound itself
that perception itself that State of
Mind of of perceiving sound doesn't
Force out of your mind the idea that
sound could be unchanging or not have
subtle imp permanence it's only the
perception that sound does change subtly
from millisecond to Mill second which
can per can shove out of your mind force
out of your mind the idea that sound
doesn't have a subtle impermanence but
it's not that the perception of sound
itself could force the idea out of your
mind that sound does not have a subtle
impermanence and it's exactly the same
case think about it carefully we're
talking about exactly the same case uh
the fact that you focus on that object
to perceive its emptiness doesn't mean
that you're perceiving that object when
you perceive it's emptiness okay
[Music]
yes m
uh don't forget where we are we're
denying this this kind of ultimate
nature of things which are dependent or
coming from their causes right and now
you know that when we say things which
are dependent on their causes don't have
an ultimate nature what we mean is when
we say they're not they don't have a
nature of being ultimate what we mean is
they are not the thing which the direct
perception of emptiness is focusing on
that's the only meaning when we say in
this case that they don't have a nature
of being ultimate now later on there'll
be a different meaning of what it is to
not have a nature which is Ultimate and
in that time we'll be saying about these
same objects that they do have a nature
of being ultimate and that's coming
later says JS kaapa don't confuse these
two issues this one is discussing
whether or not it's ultimate in the
sense of being the object of the
ultimate State of Mind meaning Ultimate
Reality and later on when we say it does
have some kind of nature of being
ultimate that'll be a different kind of
nature of being ultimate and I'll talk
about that one later so don't confuse
the two
issues uh remember when we started this
whole discussion I said we're going to
go two ways with this discussion about
whether something has a nature of being
ultimate or not right and first we were
going to deny it with regard to things
which are changing or which come from
the causes and conditions that case is
closed now let's go on to the second
[Music]
one uh now we got to go to the other way
which is denying some kind of ultimate
uh nature of being ultimate with regard
to what's called uh total existence
right which means which is a code word
in my only school for empty itself
okay uh page 13 line n for those of you
I think let's see it count
again looks like number nine looks like
number nine
[Music]
uh so now we go to the second way in
which uh something doesn't have a nature
of being ultimate and this will be
denying uh a nature of being ultimate
with regard to what we call Total
existence as you remember is a code word
for emptiness itself and that is being
treated in the Sutra where Lord Buddha
explains what he meant in the sutras uh
with wording that begins on the ninth
line on page page 13 and continues to
the final line on page 13 so that's
going to be uh the Lord Buddhist own
explanation of the second way to go when
you're talking about things not having a
nature of being ultimate and here we're
talking about uh total existence being a
code word for emptiness how they don't
have a nature of being ultimate which is
a different nature of being ultimate
right uh this the pattern here will be
the same uh first Jessa will will give
you the suu quotation and then later
he'll give you his take on the Sut
quotation and explain it for you so
again we're going to have that same
pattern of J Kapa giving you the C
quotation and then going on to his
expanded explanation of the C
quotation for
uh now when we get to the second kind of
lack of ultimate lack of nature of being
ultimate just set aside now all that one
we just talked about with things which
are dependent things which come from
their causes now let's focus on this
second kind of ultimate that doesn't
exist and as I said for this refers to
the gaka or the thing which Emptiness is
empty of okay the non-existent thing
which never was there whose lack is
called emptiness we're talking about
that one and the ultimate thing which we
deny when we talk about emptiness is a
self nature of objects right as opposed
to self nature of self right this is the
ultimate one the self- nature we are
denying uh the lack of of we are denying
the the self nature of of objects of
things okay as opposed to to as opposed
to the person and in this case it means
uh the the parts of a person okay we're
denying that they have any ultimate
existence and it's not just the case
that we're saying that total existence
don't forget when I say that I'm talking
about emptiness we're not just saying
that total existence is a lack of that
non-existent thing but rather is what he
meant when he was doing this it's the
total opposite of that thing it's not
just the lack of that kind of
self-existence it is the very object
which is defined directly by the absence
of that other object so you you flop you
pancake over that other thing and you
reach emptiness so so it's not just that
oh this is something which lacks that
kind of ultimate existence it is the
opposite of that it is the very absence
of that ultimate existence see the
difference it is not something which
doesn't possess that kind of timate
existence it is defined as the absence
of that kind of ultimate existence so if
you just take that kind of ultimate
existence and say it doesn't exist the
you flop that pancake over then you get
to what emptiness is so it's not just
that emptiness doesn't have an ultimate
existence it is the very absence of that
ultimate existence in the second
explanation of ultimate existence as
being the thing that we deny when we
talk of emptiness the ultimate thing
which is the lack of a self- nature to
the parts of a person really or to
objects you can
say oh
boy uh I'm going to ask you a question
okay ready uh is it okay to describe
emptiness okay total existence right is
it okay to describe emptiness as simply
being something which is other than the
self-existent
thing did sound D did
some uh what would be the problem if we
just disc if we described emptiness
simply as something that wasn't the
thing which emptiness denies
what would be the problem
there if you say there's another
possibility that there Rises there if
you describe it that way well would you
uh like to tell me what that possibility
would be
okay uh that's the I got to admit you're
right Winston you know what what you
said is true uh because if you describe
emptiness as merely something that's not
a self-existent object you could be
getting into things which don't exist at
all and then you the the opening of
Canon worms but he says if we restrict
ourselves to things which actually do
exist do you still have the same problem
that you shouldn't describe emptiness as
simply being something other than the
thing which we
deny if I give a and say you oh that
covers everything and in your mind there
comes an exception and you say my it
doesn't cover everything well you better
be ready to give me this
exception so give me that exception
let's go man something which exist which
wouldn't be covered properly if we
described it as simply being other than
a self-existent thing rather than the
total absence or the the simple absence
of that self-existent thing
well other than the self-existent thing
doesn't that imply that the
self-existent thing actually exists oh
that's pretty
[Music]
[Laughter]
good uh you didn't what there must be
nice uh you tried to go somewhere but
you just kind of squeaked
[Laughter]
a you tried to make a move but you just
twitched you're still sitting in that
chair s squ sreaming around you didn't
get up off that chair
what's wrong with describing emptiness
as simply as being something other than
a self-existent thing why do you have to
say Emptiness is that very thing which
is which comes out when you deny the
self-existent
thing would there be confusion between
the emptiness and the bases
ofan emptiness and the basis of
emptiness were
bothi as
being for
uh we need something that is other than
which exists which is other than the
object which emptiness denies and
something which about it which we can't
say that it's that it exists
ultimately exist ultimately in my yeah
in the Min
School how about uh how about uh an
imaginary
[Music]
any of the
imaginary so can you say about
constructs that they have a nature of
being ultimate or do you have to say
about constructs that they don't have a
nature of being
ultimate they don't have a nature in
themselves of being ultimate uh
you can't say can't
say you're you're getting close you're
getting hot
uh you guys are like somebody screwing
us screw into the wood and suddenly hit
a hard place and you're stuck
there but you're getting closer don't
focus on he said don't
Focus
the the object we have to see the object
first Focus
per
M uh yeah I know that's a little bit
different that's a yeah that's a tough
one that's a tough
one you uh put the screw pretty far into
the wall you want to try to screw it in
the rest
[Laughter]
away uh so among the
how many of the three groups of the Mind
only school can be characterized as
being as not having a nature of being
ultimate have been characterized just
the first just
the not being is not being the ultimate
no it's not having a nature being what
were those two things we talking about
theultimate
[Music]
yeah uh and what was the one that didn't
make it into the group which group was
it that didn't make it
in
construct so now I ask you a
question our mental
constructs that very subtle form of self
existence called the self-existence of
objects are they
that are they the thing that emptiness
denies are they the ultimate thing that
emptiness denies are they the ultimate
form of the gaka are mental constructs
the ultimate form of the
gaka in school
uh you got real close to children so he
says uh if you describe uh the meaning
of not to have a nature which is
Ultimate as simply being something which
is not the thing which emptiness denies
then people might start thinking that
constructs uh were the thing that with
that okay and then the third group would
be getting into this group of not having
nature of being ultimate so that's the
problem that comes up if you
describe
uh the that kind of lack of ultimate
existence nature of being ultimate as
simply something which is not that thing
which is the ultimate thing which we
deny if you just describe a lack of
nature of being ultimate if you describe
it simply as oh that thing which is not
the thing which emptiness denies then
people might mistake Al constructs for
that because everybody knows mental
constructs are not that ultimate thing
which emptiness denies so that's why we
can't describe that emptiness simply as
anything which is not the ultimate thing
which emptiness denies you have to say
it's the exact opposite of that rather
than saying it's just something other
than that okay that's why because then
you'd be getting into what we call
constructs because they are something
which is not what emptiness ultimately
denies but they you can't say about them
that they are uh don't have any nature
of being ultimate because that doesn't
apply to group number two it only
applies to group number one and group
number
three okay got it I don't
know uh one I mean uh uh Shang two I
mean k and three I mean yungu
okay how are we doing on that
[Laughter]
[Music]
so if you say it in a debate like this
right let's consider yungu which means
uh emptiness itself okay uh it doesn't
have a nature of being ultimate
because it's not something which is the
ultimate thing that emptiness denies is
that a good reason or not is that a good
logical proof or not I'll say it again
let's consider emptiness itself okay it
doesn't have a nature of being ultimate
because it is not that thing which
emptiness denies it's that is that
airtight you have to say no you have to
sayun not necessarily so because there
are lots of things which are not the
thing which emptiness denies which are
still not characterized as not having a
nature which is Ultimate and those are
K yeah so it's not air it's not an
airtight
proof therefore it's very important not
to describe emptiness or what we call
Total existence as being simply that
which is is not the object which
emptiness denies but rather to describe
it or to characterize it as being the
exact opposite or the simple absence of
the object which emptiness denies and
that is what emptiness is you can't
characterize emptiness as being oh that
thing which is not what emptiness denies
you have to characterize it as that
simple absence of what emptiness denies
and the simple absence of what emptiness
denies is a better way to describe
emptiness than to say that thing which
is not the thing which we deny
okay and and isn't it true that we have
to say in a debate that constructs even
though they are not the object which
emptiness denies they could never be
characterize as the direct opposite the
pancake flop of the thing which
emptiness denies you couldn't never
describ that way so isn't it true that
we couldn't say that about constructs
they can't be described as the the
diametric opposite of the thing which
emptiness denies they can only be
characterized as something which is not
the thing which emptiness denies so the
converse is true as
well m
so we we've gotten up to page 14 line
four and this is where exactly the same
thing is being said everything we just
talked about is being stated here in the
book okay uh where it says that uh that
the the sense in which emptiness itself
doesn't have a nature of being ultimate
is that it doesn't have it is the direct
diametric opposite of something which
would be self-existent rather than
simply something other than something
which was self-existent okay all
right uh he said and he described it as
being the diametric opposite the total
the very absence of that thing the meog
okay
uh we get here we've reached another
very subtle point on which the
omniscient Jona has made a little boo
boo and without and without mentioning
him by name uh Justin C is goingon to
needle
[Laughter]
him fore
and here's a very subtle Point um the
omnicient CH has said to Jets Kapa you
know you're characterizing emptiness and
by the way you can use three different
words you can say Yong dup which means
I'm calling toally we might have to
adjust it later okay uh yondu which is
emptiness or you could say that very
most subtle form of lack of self- nature
to objects or you could call it
emptiness anyway whatever you call it
these three things which are all Sy
synonymous says jonan to jetona uh
you're characterizing them as the simple
absence of a self-existent you know
you're characterizing them as the
diametric opposite of a self-existent
thing but when you think about it uh
when you perceive emptiness when you
think of emptiness you are thinking of
it as some kind of independent positive
object and almost in the same way that
you perceive a a water picture you see
you are making in your mind some
positive uh self-standing picture of the
thing and that's how you're perceiving
emptiness so you Jona are describing
empt uh emptiness as the absence as a
lack as a negative as an as a thing uh
simply the the simple absence of of this
particular object but when you think
about it Joka when you when you are
thinking about the idea of emptiness
isn't it true that you're making some
kind of positive mental image almost in
the same way that you do when you are
perceiving a a water picture or
something like that
uh today we won't cover this in many
detail we'll just set out the path on
which we're going to travel uh or just
have set out the path I'm going travel
and then uh tomorrow we'll discuss it in
Greater detail but I just wanted to get
you off now we got a little bit of a
start on the hassle the philosophical
hassle that's going to arise tomorrow
okay
[Music]
sh
[Laughter]
fore it's F old
time that's
[Laughter]